Finding Aid for Russell N. DeJong papers 1942-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Russell N. DeJong papers
1942-1979
DeJong, Russell N.
851075 Aa 2
Professor and chairman of the department of neurology of the University of Michigan Medical School and the University Hospital. Papers document his teaching and research and participation in professional organizations.
23 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. DeJong and came to the library in several accessions beginning in 1962. The donor number for the collection is 255
The collection is open for research.
Russell Nelson DeJong, professor and chairman of the department of neurology of the University of Michigan Medical School and the University Hospital, was born on March 12, 1907, in Orange City, Iowa. He attended Grand Rapids Junior College for two years, then entered the University of Michigan where he received his B.A. in 1929, a Doctor of Medicine degree in 1932, and a Master of Science degree in Neurology in 1936.
In 1932, DeJong joined the staff of the University Hospital as a intern in neurology. He became assistant resident in 1933, instructor in 1934, assistant professor in 1937, associate professor in 1941, and professor and chairman of the neurology department in 1950. As chairman, DeJong enjoyed success both as a recruiter of clinicians and teachers for his department and as an accomplished grantsman acquiring funds to further his and the research interests of his colleagues.
DeJong understood the importance of improving the training given in neurology and the quality of research conducted in the fields of neuroanatomy and neurophysiology. He was the author of The Neurologic Examination and A History of American Neurology, as well as numerous contributions to professional journals. DeJong further demonstrated his belief that the members of his profession should share their research when he accepted the position of editor-in-chief of Neurology. He held this position from 1951 to 1976. In addition, DeJong was neurology editor of the Yearbook of Neurology and Neurology and on the editorial boards of Handbook of Clinical Neurology and of Excerpta Medica. As editor of Neurology, DeJong was noted for his skill both in selecting material and in assisting authors to improve their submissions.
DeJong's accomplishments go beyond his work as a clinician, teacher, and administrator. He was also a researcher of note whose interests were varied. This included research and participation in organizations concerned with multiple sclerosis, Parkinson's disease, migraine, Huntington's Choreaepilepsy, Guillain-Barrè syndrome. Among the organizations that DeJong actively participation in were the American Epilepsy Association, the National Institute of Neurological Diseases and Blindness, the American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, the World Federation of Neurology, the American Academy of Neurology, the American Neurological Association, and the National Multiple Sclerosis Society.
DeJong died August 20, 1990.
Summary Contents List
Correspondence (boxes 1-3)
Professional Organizations (boxes 3-14) American Academy of Neurology (boxes 3-10) Other Organizations (boxes 10-14)
University of Michigan (boxes 14-17)
Published Papers (box 17)
Miscellaneous (boxes 17-23)
The Russell DeJong papers documents the activities of an individual who, through his teaching, research, and commitment to his profession, achieved national and international prominence in the field of neurology. The collection has been arranged into six series: Correspondence, Professional Organizations, University of Michigan, Published Papers, Miscellaneous, and Photographs.
Subjects:
DeJong, Russell N.; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Neurology.
Subjects - Visual Material:
DeJong, Russell N.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, dating from around 1942 to 1975, is arranged alphabetically within three broad sequences of years. These files include both miscellaneous lettered folders as well as folders for individual correspondents. These files relate to professional activities and interests.
  - Correspondence file A-Z, circa 1942-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence file A-H, circa 1960-1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence file I-Z, circa 1960-1970 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence A-K, circa 1969-1975 (Box 2)
    (includes people files dating back to the 1950s)
  - Correspondence L-Z, circa 1969-1975 (Box 3)
- Professional Organizations
  Professional Organizations is the largest series within the collections and concerns DeJong's various activities within the field of neurology. This series is arranged alphabetically by the name of organization. The major portion of this series relates to DeJong's involvement with the American Academy of Neurology, and most particularly with DeJong's editorship of Neurology.
  - American Academy of Neurology
    - General, 1947-1979; 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Committee on Education, 1948-1952; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Membership Committee, 1964-1969 (Box 4)
    - Neurology editorial board files (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (include reports, lists, correspondence, etc.) (Box 5)
      - 1949-1966
        - Adams, Raymond, 1950-1955 (Box 5)
        - Bailey, Pearce, 1950-1961 (Box 5)
        - Benton, Arthur, 1960-1966 (Box 5)
        - Brown, Joe R., 1957-1966 (Box 5)
        - Buchanan, Douglas, 1952-1953 (Box 5)
        - Carpenter, Malcolm, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
        - Daly, David, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
        - Haymaker, Webb, 1950-1955 (Box 5)
        - Hoefer, Paul, 1949-1952 (Box 5)
        - Katzman, Robert, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
        - Landau, William, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
        - Mackay, Ro, 1954-1966 (Box 5)
        - Magee, Kenneth, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
        - Masten, Mabel (became associate editor in 1954), 1950-1963 (Box 5)
        - Merritt, H. Houston, 1954-1962 (Box 5)
        - Morrell, Frank, 1959-1966 (Box 5)
        - Netsky, Martin, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
        - O'Leary, James, 1957-1963 (Box 5)
        - Pfeiffer, Carl, 1959-1966 (Box 5)
        - Pope, Alfred, 1959-1963 (Box 5)
        - Richardson, E.P., 1955-1966 (Box 5)
        - Richter, Richard, 1949-1966 (Box 5)
        - Robb, J. Preston, 1955-1966 (Box 5)
        - Rose, Augustus, 1952-1957 (Box 6)
        - Shy, G. Milton, 1966 (Box 6)
        - Snider, Ray S., 1959-1965 (Box 6)
        - Swanson, August, 1966 (Box 6)
        - Toman, James, 1959-1965 (Box 6)
        - Tower, Donald, 1957-1966 (Box 6)
        - Vonderahe, Donald, 1950-1963 (Box 6)
        - Walker, A. Earl, 1950-1966 (Box 6)
        - Ward, Arthur A., Jr., 1966 (Box 6)
        - Wartenberg, Robert, 1949-1966 (Box 6)
        - Wood, Ernest H., 1966 (Box 6)
        - Yakovlev, Paul, 1954-1963 (Box 6)
      - 1967-1973
        - Benton, Arthur, 1967-1969; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Brown, Joe R., 1967-1972; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Carpenter, Malcolm, 1967-1972; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Daly, David, 1967-1972; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Greer, Melvin, 1968-1972 (Box 6)
        - Heyman, Albert, 1968-1972 (Box 6)
        - Jampel, Robert, 1967-1972 (Box 6)
        - Katzman, Robert, 1967-1972; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Landau, William, 1967-1972; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Mackay, Ro, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
        - Magee, Kenneth, 1967-1972; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Morrell, Frank, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
        - Netsky, Martin, 1967-1972; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Pfeiffer, Carl, 1967-1972 (Box 7)
        - Richardson, E.P., 1967-1972 (Box 7)
        - Richter, Richard, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
        - Robb, J. Preston, 1967-1972 (Box 7)
        - Shy, G. Milton, 1967 (Box 7)
        - Swanson, August, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
        - Swanson, Phillip, 1969-1972 (Box 7)
        - Tower, Donald, 1967 (Box 7)
        - Ward, Arthur A., Jr., 1967-1972 (Box 7)
        - Wood, Ernest H., 1967-1972 (Box 7)
      - 1973-1974
        - Appel, Stanley H. (Box 7)
        - Barnett, H.J.M. (Box 7)
        - Cohen, Maynard M. (Box 7)
        - Dodge, Phillip R. (Box 7)
        - Earle, Kenneth M. (Box 7)
        - Engle, Andrew G. (Box 7)
        - Gazzaniga, Michael S. (Box 7)
        - Gilman, Sid (Box 7)
        - Goldensohn, Eli S. (Box 7)
        - Greer, Melvin (Box 7)
        - Heyman, Albert (Box 7)
        - Jampel, Robert S. (Box 7)
        - Joynt, Robert J. (Box 8)
        - Magee, Kenneth R. (Box 8)
        - Merlis, Jerome K (Box 8)
        - Moosy, John (Box 8)
        - Swanson, Phillip D. (Box 8)
        - Taveras, Juan (Box 8)
        - Victor, Maurice (Box 8)
      - 1975 (includes some, 1974, 1976
        - Alter, Milton (Box 8)
        - Appel, Stanley H. (Box 8)
        - Barnett, H.J.M. (Box 8)
        - Cohen, Maynard M. (Box 8)
        - Dodge, Phillip R. (Box 8)
        - Dyck, Peter (Box 8)
        - Earle, Kenneth M. (Box 8)
        - Engle, Andrew G. (Box 8)
        - Gazzaniga, Michael S. (Box 8)
        - Gilman, Sid (Box 8)
        - Goldensohn, Eli S. (Box 8)
        - Greer, Melvin (Box 8)
        - Heyman, Albert (Box 8)
        - Jampel, Robert S. (Box 8)
        - Joynt, Robert J. (Box 8)
        - McFarlin, Dale E. (Box 8)
        - Magee, Kenneth R. (Box 8)
        - Merlis, Jerome K (Box 8)
        - Moosy, John (Box 8)
        - Sutlin, Jerome, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
        - Swanson, Phillip D. (Box 8)
        - Taveras, Juan (Box 8)
        - Victor, Maurice (Box 8)
        - Ward, Arthur, 1973-1975 (Box 8)
      - 1976
        - Alter, Milton (Box 8)
        - Appel, Stanley H. (Box 8)
        - Barnett, H.J.M. (Box 8)
        - Cohen, Maynard M. (Box 8)
        - Dodge, Phillip R. (Box 8)
        - Dyck, Peter (Box 8)
        - Earle, Kenneth M. (Box 8)
        - Engle, Andrew G. (Box 8)
        - Gazzaniga, Michael S. (Box 8)
        - Gilman, Sid (Box 8)
        - Goldensohn, Eli S. (Box 8)
        - Greer, Melvin (Box 8)
        - Heyman, Albert (Box 8)
        - Jampel, Robert S. (Box 8)
        - Joynt, Robert J. (Box 8)
        - McFarlin, Dale E. (Box 8)
        - Magee, Kenneth R. (Box 8)
        - Merlis, Jerome K (Box 8)
        - Moosy, John (Box 8)
        - Rowland, Lewis P. (Box 8)
        - Swanson, Phillip D. (Box 8)
        - Taveras, Juan (Box 8)
        - Victor, Maurice (Box 8)
        - Ward, Arthur (Box 8)
    - Neurology working files (Box 9)
      - Correspondence to, 1955 (Box 9)
      - Yearly file for, 1962 (Box 9)
      - Yearly file for, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Other organizations
    - American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology (Box 10)
      - 1950-1974, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - Residency Review Committee for Psychiatry and Neurology, 1954-1966; 3 folders (Box 10)
    - American Epilepsy Society, 1958-1971 (scattered) (Box 10)
    - American League Against Epilepsy, 1945-1956 (scattered) (Box 10)
    - American Medical Association, 1953-1964 (Box 11)
      (mainly reviews of exhibits and responses in question and answer column of AMA journal)
    - American Neurological Association, 1963-1979; 7 folders (Box 11)
    - American Psychiatric Association, 1943-1966 (Box 11)
    - Association of University Professors of Neurology, 1971-1975 (Box 11)
    - Central Neuropsychiatric Association, 1953-1967 (scattered) (Box 11)
    - Cerebral Palsy Committee, 1951-1952 (Box 11)
    - Clinical Neurology Information Center, 1972-1974 (Box 11)
    - Huntington's Chorea Foundation, 1967-1978; 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Huntington's Disease research group, 1967-1971 (Box 12)
    - International Affairs Joint Committee of ANA and AAN, 1963-1965; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - International Congress of Neuro-genetics and Neuro-ophthalmology, 1967 (Box 12)
    - International Congress of Neurological Sciences (later International Congress of Neurology), 1957-1969; 3 folders (Box 12)
      (also includes related world congresses)
    - International Representation of American Neurology, Joint Committee on, 1959-1961 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Multiple Sclerosis Society, 1956-1974; 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Michigan Neurological Association, 1968-1979; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Michigan Society of Neurology and Psychiatry, 1941-1968; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Michigan State Medical Society, 1944-1974 (Box 12)
    - Muscular Dystrophy Society, 1950-1969 (Box 12)
    - National Committee for the Control of Huntington's Disease and its Consequences, 1975-1976 (Box 13)
    - National Conference on Education in the Neurological Sciences, 1966 (Box 13)
    - National Institute of Health. Neurology Study Section, 1958-1962 (Box 13)
    - National Institute of Neurological Diseases and Blindness (later Neurological Diseases and Stroke, 1951-1976; 4 folders (Box 13)
    - National Multiple Sclerosis Society, 1950-1979; 8 folders (Box 13)
    - National Research Council, Drug Efficacy Study: Centrally acting muscle relaxants, 1966-1969 (Box 14)
    - Residency Review Committee for Psychiatry and Neurology, AMA (University of Chicago review) (Box 14)
    - U.S. Public Health Service. Neurological and Sensory Disease Service, 1962-1967 (Box 14)
    - World Federation of Neurology
      - General, 1961-1968; 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Journal proposal, 1958 (Box 14)
      - Madrid meeting, 1963-1964 (Box 14)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series consists of materials pertaining to the University of Michigan Department of Neurology and to DeJong's other university activities.
  - Administrators Files
    - Associate deans, communications with, 1969-1974 (Box 14)
    - Furstenberg, A.C., 1949-1959 (Box 14)
    - Gronvall, John, 1970-1973 (Box 14)
    - Hubbard, W.N., 1959-1970; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Kerlikowske, A.C., 1964-1969 (Box 14)
    - Nelson, Roger B., 1963-1968 (Box 14)
    - Sheldon, John M., 1960-1965 (Box 14)
    - Votaw, Charles (re curriculum study), 1972 (Box 14)
  - Affirmative action, 1972-1973 (Box 14)
  - Cerebrovascular Insufficiency Study Group, 1959-1960 (Box 14)
  - Clinical Practice Committee, 1960-1962; 1964-1967; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Clinical Resource Needs Committee, 1963-1969; 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Convulsive Disorder Clinic, 1960-1966 (Box 15)
  - Course materials
    - Examination questions, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Neurology 161 course materials (Box 15)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1955-1963; 1967-1969 (Box 15)
  - Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award Committee, 1956-1958 (Box 15)
  - Intern evaluations of RND and neurology program, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Intern-Resident Committee, 1959-1964 (Box 15)
  - Junior Neurology Lectures, 1960s
    - Examinations (Box 15)
    - Schedules (Box 15)
  - Kenneth Campbell Foundation for Neurological Research, 1964-1974 (Box 15)
  - Kresge Hearing Research Institute, 1960-1962 (Box 15)
  - Lectures
    - Nursing (Box 15)
    - Physical therapy (Box 15)
    - Psychiatry residents (Box 15)
  - Lederle Award Committee (Box 15)
  - Neurology Dept.
    - Budgets, (scattered), 1949-1963/64; 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Budgets, 1964/65-1967/68; 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Review and Search Committee, 1975 (Box 16)
    - Staff communications, 1969-1971 (Box 16)
    - Staff meetings, 1972-1975; 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Letters of congratulations upon appointment as chairman, 1950 (Box 16)
  - Neuro-opthalmology course (Box 16)
  - Neuropathology Laboratory Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
  - Ophthalmology-Search Committee for Head of Dept. of Ophthalmology, 1967; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Otolaryngology Committee, 1960 (Box 16)
  - Phi Chi fraternity, 1958-1963 (Box 16)
  - Postgraduate medicine and courses, 4 folders (Box 16)
  - Professional Fees-Steering Committee for the Study of Professional Fees (Box 16)
  - Residents schedules (Box 16)
  - Residency training program, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Retirement Committee, 1956-1957 (Box 17)
  - Speech Clinic, 1944-1967 (Box 17)
  - Tenure Committee, 1957 (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Hospital
    - Correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 17)
    - House staff correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 17)
    - Outpatient Department, 1962-1975 (Box 17)
  - University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Celebration, 1964 (Box 17)
- Published materials
  Published Papers is a series of DeJong's writings.
  - Abstracts of papers, etc. (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series is unprocessed and not further described.
  - Unprocessed files (Box 17)
  - Unprocessed files (Box 18)
  - Unprocessed files (Box 19)
  - Unprocessed files (Box 20)
  - Unprocessed files (Box 21)
  - Unprocessed files (Box 22)
  - Unprocessed files (Box 23)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series consists of portraits of DeJong, collected portraits of other prominent physicians, and photos of DeJong at university and professional meetings.
  - Portraits of Russell N. DeJong and other prominent neurologists; photos of RND as part of larger groups (Box 23)